Guide to the School of Art, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
School of Art, Yale University, records
1950-1998
RU 291
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
The records consist of subject files, correspondence, printed material, posters, and films documenting the administration, staff, and students of the Yale School of Art and its predecessors. Records documenting the Planning and Priorities Committee and the Graphic Art Department are also included as well as records of the Yale Center for American Art and Material Culture.
Yale University. School of Art
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 20-A (YRG 20-A), Central records and records of the dean of the Yale School of Art
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the materials is partially restricted. See inventory for details.Original film is restricted. Researchers needing to consult the original materials should refer to a reference archivist for policies and procedures governing reproduction for access
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession
Biographical / Historical
The study of visual arts at Yale began in 1832 with the opening of the Trumbull Gallery, the first art museum in the country to be connected with a college. A successful exhibition there in 1858 generated interest in formalized studies in art at Yale. The School of Fine Arts (1869-1955), made possible by a gift from Augustus Street (B.A. 1812), began soon thereafter and was established with the completion of Street Hall. A professorship in Painting and Design was created and the School was formally opened in 1869. The first Bachelor of Fine Arts was conferred in 1891. Courses in architecture began in 1908, and drama, a part of the School until 1955, was added in 1925. In 1928 the Yale Art Gallery was opened. A large addition to the Gallery, designed by Louis Kahn, opened in 1953. From 1955-1958, the School was briefly renamed the School of Architecture and Design. The designation of School of Art and Architecture was adopted in 1958 and used until 1971. In 1969, the internal organization of the faculty was led to the creation of the Faculty in Art and the Faculties in Design and Planning. In 1972 this action was formalized by the creation of two autonomous schools: the School of Art (1972- ) and the School of Architecture (1972- ). The two schools remain closely associated but are administratively separate
Scope and Contents
The records consist of subject files, correspondence, printed material, posters, and films documenting the administration, staff, and students of the Yale School of Art and its predecessors. Records documenting the Planning and Priorities Committee and the Graphic Art Department are also included as well as records of the Yale Center for American Art and Material Culture.
Architecture -- Study and teaching; Art schools; Art -- Study and teaching; Graphic arts -- Study and teaching; Schools of architecture; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Audiotapes; Motion pictures (visual works); Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. School of Architecture and Design; Yale University. School of Art and Architecture; Yale University. School of Art; Yale University. School of Fine Arts
- Film Department instructional and conceptual films, circa 1971-1974; Accession 1980-A-001
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Last Class, silent film (1100'), 1 (Box 1)
  - Last Class, sound reel (16mm, 1100') (Box 2)
  - World Order Documentary (900'), 1 (Box 3)
  - Voyage To Next (Faith Hubley) (100'), 1 (Box 4)
  - 15-16-17 (800'), 1 (Box 5)
  - 15-16-17 (1200'), 1 (Box 6)
  - 15-16-17, sound reel (16mm, 1000') (Box 7)
  - World Order Documentary, sound reel (16mm) (Box 8)
  - Dizzy Gillespie (Faith Hubley), 1 (Box 9–10)
- Records of the dean of the School of Art, circa 1981-1996; Accession 2001-A-014
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2031
  - Priorities and planning
    - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1982-83 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brissago
    - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Film, audiotape, printed material, and student and personnel records, 1959-1986; Accession 2001-A-085; 1 (Box 1)
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2021
  Scope and Contents
  No inventory available
- Records and printed materials of the School of Art, circa 1950-1991; Accession 2001-A-096
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2026
  - Records of correspondence with alumni, circa 1956-1977 (Box 1)
  - Celebration of 40 Years of Graphic Design at Yale, 1990-1991
    - Printing samples (Box 2)
    - Speeches (Box 2)
    - Timelines (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Invitations/RSVP/ invite lists (Box 2)
  - Records of Alvin Eisenman as chairman of the Graphic Design Dept., 1956-1974
    - Student records (Box 3)
    - Commencement records (Box 3)
  - Building at Yale under A.B. Giamatti, 1 binder, 1976-1987 (Box 4)
  - Materials concerning the Bradbury Thompson celebratory dinner, 1 binder (Box 4)
  - Herbert Matter Archive Project, 2 binders, 1989 (Box 4)
- Poster archive from the Graphic Design Dept, circa 1966-1991; Accession 2001-A-107
  - 1966 (Box 1)
    General
    This material has been removed from this box and put into containers 1A, 1B, 1C, 1D, and 1E.
    - Yale Symphony Plays The Lone Ranger and Other Oldies But Goodies (Box 1)
    - Christopher Pullman (Folder 1C)
  - 1969
    - Colossal Monument (Box 1)
    - Claes Oldenburg (Folder 1E)
  - 1972
    - Four Directions in Modern Photography (Folder 1D)
  - 1974
    - Yale in China (Folder 1C)
  - 1976
    - Schutz, A German Requiem (Folder 1B)
    - An Exhibition of Graphic Art from the Offenbacher Werkstatt and the Studio of Fritz Kredal. (Folder 1B)
  - 1977
    - Chamber Orchestra of New England (Folder 1A)
  - 1978 (Box 2)
    This material has been removed from this box and put into containers 2A, 2B, 2C, and 2D.
    - Barber, Prokofiev, Falla (Box 2)
  - 1980
    - A Night at the Yale Symphony Orchestra (Box 2)
    - Halloween Concert (Box 2)
  - circa 1981
    - Graduate Thesis Exhibition (Folder 2C)
  - 1982
    - Philharmonia (Folder 2B)
    - Pathetique (Folder 2B)
  - 1983
    - Brahms, Berlioz, Hayden (Folder 2A)
  - 1984
    - Herbert Matter (Folder 2A)
  - 1987 (Box 3)
    This material has been removed from this box and put into containers 3A, 3B, 3C, 3D, and 3E.
    - Sarcophagus (Folder 3E)
  - circa 1987
    - The Peterdi Years: An Exhibition (Folder 3D)
  - 1988
    - Tour 88, Yale Symphony Orchestra (Folder 3D)
    - The Restoration of the Sistine Chapel (Folder 3C)
    - Beinecke 25 (Box 3)
    - Jan Murray (Folder 3C)
  - circa 1988
    - Pathetique (Folder 3B)
  - circa 1989
    - Yale Philharmonica (Folder 3B)
  - 1991
    - Exhibit of Undergraduate Work (Folder 3A)
    - Mozart, Mozart, Brahms (Folder 3A)
  - no date (Box 4)
    This material has been removed from this box and put into containers 4A, 4B, 4C, and 4D.
    - Health Care Delivery (Folder 4A)
    - Bauer, Smotrich (Box 4)
    - Yale School of Art, Undergraduate Work Opening (Folder 4A)
    - Eli Kince (Box 4)
    - Yale Film Festival (Folder 4B)
    - Noah Webster, Advocate for Americanism (Folder 4C)
    - Take the Minibus, it's safer than walking. (Folder 4D)
    - Monuments, Memorials and Public Spaces (Folder 4D)
    - Yale Pro-Am Invitational Squash Tournament (Folder 4D)
- Faculty correspondence, 1970-1998; Accession 2003-A-004
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2033
- Records concerning the Yale Center for American Art and Material Culture, 1973-1998; Accession 2013-A-003
  Restricted until January 1, 2030.
  - McNeil Fellowships, 1984-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Robert McNeil correspondence, 1973-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Robert McNeil correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Robert McNeil correspondence, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Material Culture Center - space and operations, Circa 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)